I recently released my own supplement
protocol and in it I received a lot of
requests to do one for people that are
how do I say this delicately
more seasoned than I am like this
comment.
Wait a minute. Not that one. Damn spam
comments. Here we go. Anyway, I'm going
to pretend like thousands of people
asked me for this and I didn't just
isolate a single comment to make it seem
like there's a mass interest. I thought
to myself, why not just rope my family
in on this? So, if you're an OG
Physionic subscriber, you might remember
this gentleman, Father Physionic, also
known by his real name, Dean. Dean, or
Papa as I call him, has his PhD in
physics. And now that I have my PhD in
molecular medicine, I'm his source for
supplement advice and he's my source for
existential crisis. So, what does he
take and why did I recommend these for
him? So, I have this mix of um
supplements that I make once every two
weeks. I mix up a bunch of powders. And
here I have for uh one day I have 2 g of
glycine, 2 and 1/2 g of n acetal cyine,
6 g of creatine, 8 g of collagen and 1 g
of torine.
So I take that once a day um presently
before going to bed. And I also have
these um
supplements in capsule and pill form.
We'll discuss this first half of his
stack before getting into the second
half that he's about to get into. So
first I coerced them into taking GLAC
which is glycine and nacetylcyine
because there are a few extremely
impressive randomized control trials
that indicate that gloak is extremely
beneficial across a huge number of
health metrics for those over the age of
60. I've covered these extensively in
other content including analyses of all
the data and the mechanisms. I won't
regurgitate things here. I am still
slightly apprehensive about this one
considering that I'd like to see even
more studies. But as it stands, the
benefit lost is too great not to
experiment on my father. I mean, ask him
to consider the supplement in an ethical
and loving manner. The next supplement
in his powdered stack is one of my
all-time favorites, creatine. Again, if
you've been following my work for even a
millisecond, you'll know that I've
released extensive content on the
various studies that firmly indicate
widespread benefit of creatine from
sleep deprivation, muscle performance,
cognitive benefits, muscle growth, and
more. I was a little surprised that he's
taking six grams, which I commented on.
I'm curious why six g of creatine. That
is an odd number to choose.
I don't know. Some influencer I listened
to told me. I don't know if he said it
in one of his videos or I texted him
directly
and he did not say six grams.
Is that too much?
It doesn't. Six grams is fine. It's just
uh just the usual number is five grams
that people take or if you want to go up
to five is an odd number though. like
six seems much better to me and I'm
getting kind of old so like an extra
gram probably doesn't hurt.
Okay. Well, typically for the the brain
they go up to 20 grams now, but uh five
grams has also been shown to be
effective for other uh organ systems.
Just for the brain, some studies use 20
grams, but you don't have to go up to
that high. I'm just I was just curious
about specifically six grams. I don't
think I've ever said that in my life.
Six grams. Well, I didn't pull it out of
the air. I can tell you that. Okay.
Well, you could look for the receipts
then. So, as you heard, five grams is
the typical dose, but some studies go up
to 20 grams if you're focusing more on
the cognitive benefits. The next one was
collagen. I've covered collagen up to
now with a primary focus on skin, but
there is some evidence on its impact for
the joints. But when asking my dad why
he takes it, I seem to have been wrong
in my assumption that he chooses to take
collagen for the joints primarily.
Collagen we just went over for you.
You're taking it for joints, then you're
taking it for skin, I guess, is just
kind of an additional kind of throwaway
benefit that that might be there. It's
not working very well. Actually, I was
taking it to maintain my youthful
appearance and then for I mean, if it
helps my joints, that's good, too,
because they're getting kind of sore.
Okay. Okay. It's working great.
[Laughter]
Okay. So, I stand corrected. He's taking
it for the skin, too. That said, I have
no idea where the 8 g came from.
Not from me. The usual dose in trials is
closer to 10 grams of collagen peptides.
Then we turned our attention to torine
because there have been a few scary
studies in relation to torine that I've
covered extensively. On a positive note,
torine has been linked to multiple
trials and experimental studies to have
significant benefit on metabolic
syndrome as well as multiple areas of
longevity. On the negative note, it's
been tied to cancer as well as been
shown not to decline with age as once
believed. I've covered both of these
critiques and I'll address them here. I
know people are going to ask about
touring because there's a few studies
that just recently came out negatively
against touring. Um, but yeah, I saw
your video on that.
Yeah. Well, he's not dead yet, so
I'm feeling fine. I mean, honestly, feel
great.
Uh, so that's all the proof you need.
Um,
uh, end of one as they say, but I mean
it's me, so that's all we need.
Um, yeah. So, I mean, the the studies on
torine are are perfectly fine still.
There's a few studies that have been
pushed back uh for
for
reasons that are
once you understand what the studies
actually indicate, there's no indication
to stop torine consumption or anything
like that. All the intervention trials
that have done that have been done on
torine still th those didn't just
suddenly poof disappear. Um, there's
still plenty of studies that have looked
at torine and indicated benefit from
from torine. So, yes, torine has plenty
of intervention data, meaning people are
given torine and tested before and after
consumption, and multiple trials
indicate benefit. And as for the few
studies showing negative effects, some
don't actually address torine directly,
and some change how we think about
touring, but they don't change my
perspective on if it's beneficial. So,
at this point, I'm still a fan. My dad's
dosing at one gram and plenty of
intervention studies use more. Okay,
that rounds out the powdered
supplements. I guess I'll quick add that
he also consumes one serving, about 25 g
of a protein powder because he doesn't
consume much protein in the day. Now,
before we get into the second half, I
have an updated list of supplements that
I've covered along with dosing and
special circumstances to use them
included in my Physionic Insiders
membership. I have a specific sections
for older individuals and why certain
supplements aren't advised for younger
individuals and more. Plus, let's not
forget the live sessions with me, the
private podcasts exclusive to the
insiders, the varieties of protocols and
guides and more, all included. And if
you want to have an alternate ending to
this video, I feel I'm like a Marvel's
movie producer. You'll also get a fun
story that my dad shares about me. You
can join through the link in the
description. Moving on to the capsule or
pill supplements in the stack.
So, I've got this um eye supplement.
Um I forget what it's called. Luteine,
zeazanthin.
Yeah. Right. Both of those are in there.
Probably some other things, too. I have
a multivitamin, one multivitamin. I have
a glucosamine pill and fish oil and
uh that yellow stuff.
Curcumin.
Well, and from turmeric.
Turmeric. Right. That's right.
Okay. So, starting with luteine and
zeazanthin. These two molecules are
paired because they tend to localize in
the retina of the eye and act as potent
antioxidants. There have been many
clinical trials indicating their benefit
if consumed over the long term. I will
link my analyses of all these studies in
the description for you. The next one
discussed is the multivitamin. Again,
there's some very mild benefits for the
brain according to some research that
I've covered, but my impression of the
data is that it's best to consume maybe
half a normal dose of a multivitamin
simply because your nutrition should
cover most of the necessary
micronutrients unless you h are like on
a heavily restricted diet. There's also
some cautions against overconumption of
certain micronutrients like folic acid
and some fats soluble vitamins like
versions of vitamin E. Let me repeat
overconumption.
Not that we don't need versions of these
nutrients. We do in the right amounts.
Now, a more interesting one is omega-3s.
And here we have many studies that
indicate the omega-3 fats are heart
healthy and brain healthy. Again, I've
covered many of these studies. However,
there is one emerging concern related to
omega-3 fats and is especially
applicable to my dad.
I'm a I'm a pretty big fan of omega-3s.
So obviously some contra indications
have come out from like atrial
fibrillation uh some heart issues, heart
rhythm issues. Have you been concerned
by that? Because do you want to talk
about that? I mean I watched your video
on that and it didn't seem to apply to
me. So um I mean I do have um an
arhythmia and I mean I haven't I mean
it's been good actually. It kind of
comes and goes but it's been good for
the last couple of years. So, um I don't
couldn't say that this is making it
worse.
Yeah. So, the omega-3 dose matters a
lot. So, the dose that you're consuming
is I haven't seen any evidence that that
leads to any sort of heart issues from
an arhythmia standpoint. And to be
clear, while it is true that some
studies indicate that higher doses, say
double, triple the dose that you're
consuming, uh increase arrhythmia,
uh and atrial fibrillation, which isn't
arrhythmia, um the overall effect. So
when you look beyond the atrial
fibrillation, you actually look at the
outcomes, the actual heart disease and
uh heart attacks, stroke, all that
stuff. Um, it either has a neutral
effect or still a benefit. So, I mean,
you have a funky heart rhythm. That's
scary for sure. I wouldn't want it. Um,
but the end result still indicates a
benefit. So, it's kind of a weird way to
get there, but at least the end result
isn't, oh, but and there's also an
increase in a particular outcome. I
think that the the one potential is that
with atrial fibrillation, one of the
risks is stroke because you get this uh
clotting that occurs in in the top uh
section of your heart in a very general
sense and that allows for clots uh to
and embed themselves in the finer
vessels of of your brain. Um but we
don't see any evidence of that. So uh
whatever problems there might be the
outcome is still a benefit. So, uh,
yeah, and again, at those doses, I
haven't seen any evidence of any of
that. So, it's not really a concern.
I've covered these data in the past as
well, and as mentioned, this tends to be
a bigger issue as the data suggests,
although I'd like to see more at higher
doses like 3 g. And the final two,
glucosamine, sulfate, and curcumin.
There's a lot to say here, too. However,
in this case, although I have covered
curcumin's role in blood sugar
regulation as well as on arthritis, the
main reason my dad takes it is for the
joint and anti-inflammatory benefits
even independent of arthritis. The
evidence on glucosamine is a bit more
mixed and offers some more mild relief,
but the evidence on curcumin for these
outcomes has been more significant, at
least in my mind. Again, I'll link my
work on them for a deeper dive. The dose
used for both is around 1500 milligrams,
but there are some formulations where
much less is needed. I cover that in my
more targeted analyses as well as for
the physionic insiders work that I've
done. Okay, one more thing my dad
noticed about timing his powdered
supplement stack that might benefit you,
especially if you have sleep issues. Of
course, this is just one man's
experience, not a control trial, so bear
that in mind.
Yeah. Okay. So, uh, tell me why you
switched cuz at one point you were
taking this. So, tell me about you how
you were taking it before and then tell
me how you're taking it now cuz you did
recently switch it. Right. So, this
mixture um with the creatine I was
taking
um after lunch and finding that I was
just often totally wiped out after
lunch. like I needed a nap and um
thought maybe it had something to do
with this. And since I have problems
sleeping um at night, I thought maybe
well maybe take it before going to bed
and maybe that'll help me sleep at night
and eliminate some of the um afternoon
slump too. And um so now I'm taking it
in the evening. I haven't done this very
long. maybe
few weeks a month. Um, and it seems to
be helping. It definitely helps um, we
fall asleep. My dad's had issues
sleeping for a long time and over the
last month or so, he's changed nothing
but the timing of when he consumes the
powder blend that he has, and it's led
to a noticeable improvement in sleep.
There are some mixed quality studies
suggesting that glycine improves sleep.
So, if you have trouble sleeping,
consider trying it. Okay, so I said this
in my video on my supplement routine,
which is quite different that the
supplements that you choose should be
tailored to your goals and
circumstances. This supplement routine
of glycine plus an acetylcysteine,
creatine, collagen, torine, luteine,
zeizanthin, a multivitamin, glucosamine,
omega-3s, and curcumin may not be right
for you. In fact, if you're under 60,
it's highly likely not right for you. I
actually explain what I take right here.
Thanks for hanging out and check out my
study analyses on each in the
description.